Guide to the Frank C. and Delia L. Porter Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Frank C. and Delia L. Porter papers
1864-1945
MS 404
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.5
(17 boxes)
The papers consist primarily of the correspondence of Frank C. Porter (1859-1946), Yale theology professor, 1891-1927, and his wife Delia Wood Lyman Porter (1858-1933), author. The papers also include notes and research material on the Yale seal and Hebrew words by Frank Porter; manuscripts; printed matter, memorabilia, and correspondence concerning the writings of Delia Porter; the autobiography of Chester Smith Lyman; and correspondence of William Porter.
Porter, Frank Chamberlin, 1859-1946
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Quincy Porter, 1946, and of the Yale Divinity School, 1953.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Frank C. Porter Papers. II. Delia L. Porter Papers. III. Miscellaneous Papers.
Biographical / Historical
FRANK CHAMBERLIN PORTER B. D. 1886
Born January 5, 1859, in Beloit, Wis.
Died January 24, 1946, in New Haven, Conn.
Father, Rev. William Porter, D.D. (B.A. Williams 1839; Andover Theological Seminary 1840-41; Union Theological Seminary 1841-1843), Brinsmade Professor of Latin at Beloit College; son of William and Mary Ann (Quincy). Porter of Lee, Mass. Mother, Ellen Gertrude (Chapin) Porter; daughter of Laertes and Laura (Colton) Chapin of Hartford, Conn.
Beloit High School and Preparatory School of Beloit College; B.A. Beloit College 1880, M.A. 1883; attended Chicago Theological Seminary 1881-1882, Hartford Theological Seminary 1884-1885, and Yale Divinity School 1885-1889 (B.D. 1886, Ph.D. 1889; Commencement speaker); ordained in First Church of Christ (Congregational), New Haven, January, 1895; teacher of mathematics and Greek Chicago High School 1882-84; on faculty Yale University 1889-1946 (instructor in Biblical Theology 1889-1891, Winkley Professor of Biblical Theology 1891-1927, and Winkley Professor emeritus 1927-46; librarian Trowbridge Reference Library 1895-1925; Nathaniel W. Taylor lecturer 1928-1929); taught in summer session Southwestern School of Theology 1911 and University of Chicago 1923, and gave courses at Haverford College 1912 and Theological Seminary of the Reformed Church, Lancaster, Pa., 1924; Bond lecturer Bangor Theological Seminary 1917 and Dudleian lecturer Harvard University Divinity School 1924; lecturer Oberlin Theological Seminary 1917 and Peking University 1924-25; D.D. Beloit College 1897 and Yale University 1931; author: "The Yercer Hara" in Biblical and Semitic Studies (1901), The Messages of the Apocalyptical Writers (1905), "The Pre-Existence of the Soul in the Book of Wisdom and in the Rabbinical Writings" in Old Testament and Semitic Studies in Honor of W. R. Harper (1907), "The Mysticism of the Hebrew Prophets" in At One With the Invisible edited by E. Hershey Sneath, '84 D.(1921), "Paul's Belief in Life After Death" in Religion and the Future Life edited by E. Hershey Sneath (1922), "The Historical and the Spiritual Understanding of the Bible" in Education for Christian Service (1922), The Mind of Christ in Paul (1930), and "Toward a Biblical Theology for the Present" in Contemporary American Theology (2d series; edited by Vergilius Ferm; 1933); contributed articles on the Apocrypha, Judith, Proselyte, Book of Revelation, etc., to Hasting's Bible Dictionary (1898-1902) and to theological journals; associate editor Journal of Biblical Literature 1917-1920, 1922-1925, 1929-30; his Collected Papers were published in 1928; the volume Studies in Early Christianity, edited by Shirley J. Case, '04 D., to honor Professor Porter and Professor Benjamin W. Bacon, '81, was published in 1928; member Society of Biblical Literature and Exegesis and American Theological Society; honorary deacon Center Church (Congregational), New Haven.
Married June 10, 1891, in New Haven, Delia Wood Lyman (Wellesley 1875-1877), daughter of Professor Chester Smith Lyman (B.A. 1837) and Delia Williams (Wood) Lyman, granddaughter of Joseph Wood (B.A. 1801), great-granddaughter of Oliver Ellsworth (Class of 1766), great-great-granddaughter of William Wolcott (B.A. 1734), and sister of Oliver E. Lyman, '76, and Chester W. Lyman, '82. Children: Lyman Edwards, '16, and William Quincy, '19. Mrs. Porter died January 16, 1933.
Death due to cerebral hemorrhage. Buried in Grove Street Cemetery, New Haven. Survived by sons, two grandchildren, and a sister, Mary Quincy Porter (Wellesley 1889-1890) of New Haven.
In 1935 Professor Porter made a gift to the University to endow the Delia Lyman Porter Social Fund in the Divinity School. A portrait of Professor Porter, a gift of the alumni of the Divinity School, was presented to the School in 1936.
Yale Obituary Record, No. 105, p. 194.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist primarily of the correspondence of Frank C. Porter (1859-1946), Yale theology professor, 1891-1927, and his wife Delia Wood Lyman Porter (1858-1933), author. The papers also include notes and research material on the Yale seal and Hebrew words by Frank Porter; manuscripts; printed matter, memorabilia, and correspondence concerning the writings of Delia Porter; the autobiography of Chester Smith Lyman; and correspondence of William Porter.
Families; Hebrew language -- Etymology; Women; Autobiographies; Authors; Clergy; Educators; Lyman, Chester Smith, 1814-1890; Porter, Delia Lyman, 1858-1933; Porter, Frank Chamberlin, 1859-1946; Porter, William; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Insignia
- Frank C. Porter Papers, Series I
  - Correspondence
    - Porter, Ellen Gertrude Chapin, 1873-1888 (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
    - Porter, Ellen Gertrude Chapin, 1889-1893 (Box 2, Folder 9-15)
    - Porter, Ellen Gertrude Chapin, 1894-1898 (Box 3, Folder 16-20)
    - Porter, Ellen Gertrude Chapin, 1899-1905 (Box 4, Folder 21-27)
    - Porter, Mary Quincy "May", 1884-1907 (Box 5, Folder 28-35)
    - Porter, Mary Quincy "May", 1908-1915 (Box 6, Folder 36-43)
    - Porter, Mary Quincy "May", 1916-1921 (Box 7, Folder 44-50)
    - Porter, Mary Quincy "May", 1922-1928 (Box 8, Folder 51-57)
    - Porter, Mary Quincy "May", 1929-1932 (Box 9, Folder 58-61)
    - Porter, William, 1891 (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - Porter, Delia Wood Lyman, 1895-1998 (Box 9, Folder 63-64)
  - Writings
    - Yale seal (Box 10, Folder 65-69)
    - Yale seal (Box 11, Folder 70-75)
    - Yale seal (Box 12, Folder 76-81)
- Delia L. Porter Papers, Series II
  - Correspondence
    - Porter, Frank Chamberlain, 1896, 1898 (Box 13, Folder 82-83)
    - Children, 1922-1930 (Box 13, Folder 84-89)
    - Porter, Mary Quincy "May", 1891-1892 (Box 13, Folder 90)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 13, Folder 91)
  - Writings
    - Christian Discussion Club (Box 13, Folder 91)
    - Christmas cards, 1906-1931 (Box 14, Folder 92-93)
    - CO Company records, 1904-1907 (Box 14, Folder 94)
    - Colonial dames, 1899 (Box 14, Folder 95)
    - England, 1914 (Box 14, Folder 96-97)
    - Europe, 1908 (Box 14, Folder 98-99)
    - Europe, 1910 (Box 15, Folder 100)
    - Factory inspector, 1906-1907 (Box 15, Folder 101)
    - Family letters, 1928-1932 (Box 15, Folder 102-106)
    - Lenten discussion, 1915-1917 (Box 16, Folder 107)
    - Lyman, Chester S., 1884-1890 (Box 16, Folder 108)
    - Newspaper articles, 1888-1989 (Box 16, Folder 109)
    - Publications (Box 16, Folder 110)
    - Rhymes, 1900-1912 (Box 16, Folder 111)
    - Spiritual training, 1922-1931 (Box 17, Folder 112)
    - Story letters (Box 17, Folder 113)
    - Summer in England, 1882 (Box 17, Folder 104)
    - 40th wedding anniversary, 1931 (Box 17, Folder 115)
    - General, 1872-1889 (Box 17, Folder 116-117)
    - Miscellanea (Box 18, Folder 118-119)
- Miscellaneous Papers, Series III
  - Porter, J. S.: Porter's Theology, vols. I-III (Box 19, Folder 120-122)
  - Porter, Mary Quincy "May"
    - Porter, Frank Chamberlain, 1879-1883, 1908-1913 (Box 20, Folder 123-128)
  - Porter, William, Jr.
    - Porter, Frank Chamberlain, 1882, undated (Box 21, Folder 129-130)
  - Porter, William, Sr.
    - Porter, Frank Chamberlain, 1881-1882 (Box 21, Folder 131)
  - Porter, Ellen Gertrude Chapin
    - Porter, Frank Chamberlain, 1881-1883 (Box 21, Folder 132)
  - Miscellanea, 1864-1940 (Box 21, Folder 133)